WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
And turnover!
I'm Alastair Bruce,
on the set of Downton Abbey!
As the show's
historical advisor,
I help cast and crew
create a world
that is true
to Britain's past.
MICHELLE DOCKERY:
I said to Alistair,
"Can I lean back
just a little bit?"
And he says, "Absolutely not,
not in front
of your grandmother."
Join me for "The Manners
of Downton Abbey,"
a Masterpiece special.
♫♫
ALASTAIR BRUCE:
The lives of the people
in Downton Abbey
are a glory of ritual
and grandeur.
ROBERT:
Welcome to Downton.
BRUCE:
A ballet of strange manners
and stiff formality.
ROBERT:
I nearly came down
in a dinner jacket tonight.
Oh, really?
Well, why not
a dressing gown,
or better still, pajamas?
BRUCE:
The aristocrats of Edwardian
England and their servants
lived by a very odd
set of rules,
a world away
from the way we behave today.
But to them, these manners were
the way they lived their life,
and what a life!
Manners came into everything--
how you dressed, how you ate,
how you stood, how you spoke.
Every detail mattered.
It said who you were
and where you belonged.
Were you from above stairs
or below?
You are a footman,
and a footman wears gloves.
So if we could begin.
These were the rules for life
at the time of Downton Abbey.
They were a secret code
that tells you everything
about Edwardian Britain.
And I'm going to let you in
on that secret.
I'm Alastair Bruce,
historian,
expert on British
royal ceremony,
and historical advisor
to cast and crew
on set at Downton Abbey.
Just in the background.
Alastair's referred to
as the Oracle.
BRENDAN COYLE:
Couldn't work without Alastair.
He just knows everything.
You give an indication to them
to come through.
He taught me how to sit
and stand and walk and talk.
That's just perfect.
MICHELLE DOCKERY:
I've sometimes said to Alastair,
"Can I lean back
just a little bit?"
And he says,
"Absolutely not,
not in front
of your grandmother."
CREW:
Here we go for rehearsal,
please, nice and quiet.
You know you've got
a military cross?
I didn't.
Which means he was pretty brave
in the trenches.
It's a constant struggle,
which I adore,
but it's so difficult
to get people back in time,
to when rules were so different.
LILY JAMES:
The body language
was very restrained.
It's not polite
to sort of slouch
or, you know,
put your hands all over,
you know, move like we do
in a modern way.
KEVIN DOYLE:
I hadn't realized that
there was also
a hierarchy downstairs.
ED SPELEERS:
It was a very dog-eat-dog world
amongst the staff.
And this coat's all right?
This coat's perfect as long as
you have that popper undone.
(laughing)
BRUCE:
I want to give you
my insider's guide
to the rules of living
at Downton Abbey.
CREW:
And turnover.
Turning, ready.
Action!
♫♫
Oh, there's poor
Lady Raven.
I really ought to go
and talk to her.
Of course,
Your Grace.
Don't call her
"Your Grace."
TOM:
I thought it was correct.
Call her "Duchess."
But why?
I don't call you
"Countess."
Certainly not!
But there's
no logic in it.
Oh no, if I were
to search for logic,
I should not look for it
among the English upper class.
Welcome to the library
of Downton Abbey,
which is not quite
as you normally see it.
The manners of Downton
are not just about
how to address a duchess
or which knife and fork
to pick up.
They're much more important
than that.
It's key to how
these people lived
and exactly
what they believed in.
As it is, my lord,
we may have to have a maid
in the dining room.
Cheer up, Carson.
There are worse things
happening in the world.
Not worse than a maid
serving a duke.
BRUCE:
Edwardian England was a time
of great change.
Both the Industrial Revolution
and the Great War
had altered everything.
Is this an instrument
of communication or torture?
It seemed that centuries of
tradition were all passing away.
And for the aristocracy,
they felt that they would lose
all of it.
Now we're to be turned
out of Downton!
Whether it was who to marry,
how to eat or what to wear,
their manners held the old order
in place
when everything else
seemed to be falling apart.
But why do the rituals,
the clothes and the customs
matter so much?
Because without them,
we would be like
the wild men of Borneo.
BRUCE:
And the best place to start
understanding Edwardian manners
is in the dining room.
Dinner is served,
Your Ladyship.
The Edwardians liked to eat
sumptuously.
Showing off was a part of it.
But it was not all about
the glorious food.
The ritual of the dining room
was at the center
of their lives.
Well, I think there are far more
important things to worry about
than whether or not Carson minds
serving cocktails.
BRUCE:
My job is to ensure that
that ritual
is historically correct.
I'm sorry,
would you excuse me, Mama?
I've got rather a headache.
CREW:
Cut there, very good.
Laura,
can I talk to you?
Where are your gloves?
They're on my lap,
I'm taking them with me.
Perfect, thanks
very much indeed.
Perfect, thanks.
LAURA CARMICHAEL:
You're sitting up straight,
your evening gloves
are on your lap,
hidden underneath your napkin.
Um, you don't rest your hands
on the table,
you have to remember
which course you're on
for which wine.
JIM CARTER:
Red, water, white,
is that right?
BRUCE:
Red, water...
absolutely, yes.
Yeah, yeah,
that's the white one.
JAMES:
We always have three glasses,
and there's the larger one
for the red,
slightly smaller for water,
and then even smaller
for the white wine.
The main thing I had to learn
I think was posture,
was this idea
of sitting up straight.
Like this?
That's perfect,
absolutely bolt upright.
Thanks very much.
The back of the chair was never
for anyone to lean back on,
as they do now.
That's purely decorative,
and it's purely so that the
footman has something to hold.
Nannies used to put knives here,
to make children
sit up straight.
Understanding your cutlery
was essential.
Failure to know your knives
might lead
to an embarrassing moment.
JAMES:
I've learnt from Alastair/
Pretty Woman,
you start from the outside
and work your way in.
Or it could be you start
from the inside
and work your way out.
Either way, it's one of the two!
Go on, then.
Teaspoon, egg spoon,
melon spoon, grapefruit spoon,
jam spoon...
Shall I tell you?
All right.
A bouillon spoon.
But I thought soup spoons
were the same as tablespoons.
Ah, so they are,
but not for bouillon,
which is drunk
from a smaller dish.
ROSAMUND:
Oh, she's just very tired.
She'll be fit as a flea
tomorrow.
CREW:
Cut, very good, thank you.
Okay, cut.
The reason we take such trouble
with the dining room scenes
is that they say grace
at the beginning,
and that makes it
the Lord's table.
And all the detail and sumptuous
display and the manners
reflect the struggle
that they all have
to achieve a similarly perfect
moral approach to life.
The immaculate presentation
was a statement
of moral correctness to all.
This is Basildon Park
in Berkshire.
It doubles as the Crawleys'
London residence.
Tomorrow, we're shooting
a dinner scene,
and the art department
spare no effort to lay the table
exactly as it would have been
90 years ago.
The Edwardians
prized complexity.
Perfection takes many hours,
as it did
for the Edwardian servants.
Small fork, big fork,
small fork.
And then in a perfect world,
on the other side,
we'd have that size knife,
that size knife,
a not that size knife,
and a spoon.
WOMAN:
Okay, let's do that then.
When the table
is being set out,
things have to be measured,
so Carson has a rod
with measurements on it,
and that determines
the place settings
between each place and the next,
between the chair
and the plate,
between the plate
and the glasses.
So everything
is measured out precisely.
Each butler would have
a measuring stick
to mark exactly where
the table settings were
in relation to each other.
So you'd start off
by just taking the first mark
and moving in the edge
of the first knife.
And then you'd be able
to bring all the others in
and then just bring it
straight up to that line.
They didn't use their fingers
without gloves on
because otherwise it would have
left a mark on the silver.
And on the measuring points,
they should be
absolutely equidistant.
Once you follow the line up
through the spoon,
through the first,
and then that's just
slightly off to the left,
that's slightly off
to the right,
and that sits in there
and it's also in direct line
with that,
you've got a place setting.
And when it's all perfect,
the last thing they did
was take a certain length--
I don't know,
it would be marked,
but this has just been made up.
Yeah, yeah.
And then they would
come right down.
You set that against that
and bring the chair out.
And then at the end of it,
you just kneel down like that
and you see a straight line.
What do you think,
it's not bad?
No, that's good.
Perfect.
What do you think?
Nothing succeeds
like excess.
BRUCE:
For the Edwardians,
the point of a sumptuous table
was to impress their guests.
Downstairs, who served what
was also a reflection
of where power lay.
You can take in
the fish and meat tonight.
James can follow
with the sauce.
But I should be
the first footman.
Of course you should.
First footmen
always take the meat.
Look at him,
he can't even balance it.
SPELEERS:
And the second footman
will bring out the second,
the sort of the side dish
or the veg.
It's a flipping insult--
just because he's ten foot tall!
SPELEERS:
And some footmen got paid more
for being taller.
So can you imagine Alfred and I,
for example,
I mean, he's six foot four,
Matt Milne,
and I'm five foot nine.
So I mean, he'd have got paid
loads of money
and I'd have been broke,
basically.
There's a lot of choreography
that goes into operating
as a footman.
Do you want me to show you?
The thing is, I need about
four people to help me out,
that's the problem.
Just imagine
if this was a long table.
So we'd have Carson
standing directly here.
The other side,
there's a working,
like I say, there's a fireplace
working very well.
You'd have me,
so his first footman,
like, ready to go,
basically.
I'm waiting for Carson's nod
to go and serve food.
So the first person I'd serve
would be the Dowager.
Don't put them like that.
They've got to be able
to get hold of them.
SPELEERS:
This is Maggie Smith,
this is
an Oscar-winner here, okay.
I'm very nervous every time
I have to sort of come around
the back of her to serve.
It's quite a nerve-wracking
experience.
Oh, lovely, what a treat.
(clanging)
Oh!
But sometimes, I'm having
to climb over dollies like this
with a tray of, like, meat
and come out
and serve round like that,
and still look poised
and come in,
and I lean in like that,
as such.
Mama, talk to her.
Talk to all of them.
Say something sensible.
SPELEERS:
And you've got to wait,
and you cannot move.
You go back, you wait,
you move off.
Now as I come in
to my third person,
Mr. Molesley,
or the second footman,
whoever that may be
or is at the time,
will come in and start
on his main, the second dish.
So peripherally, I can see him
and we lean in together.
DOYLE:
They kind of have to be
invisible.
Nothing interferes with
the sociability of the table.
ELIZABETH McGOVERN:
No one ever takes a bite
before Cora does, the hostess.
She will decide which direction
the conversation is going.
Are we ever going
to be allowed to turn?
HUGH BONNEVILLE:
Turning in dinner,
meaning that the conversation
will start
in a particular direction
as set by the hostess, Cora.
And so everyone
will speak that way.
And then after, you know,
when she turns...
It's time to turn.
BONNEVILLE:
Everyone turns and speaks
to the person on that side,
so everyone's getting
their fair share of chat.
BRUCE:
The apparently effortless ritual
of the dining room
disguised its true purpose.
It was a place to influence,
a place to exercise power,
a place to find a husband.
MARY:
How many times
am I to be ordered
to marry the man
sitting next to me at dinner?
As many times as it takes.
Marriage among the ruling
classes of Great Britain
was seldom about love,
but it was always
about power and land.
Land must, above all,
be kept in one piece
in order to give a man
the income to live by
and the right by which
he could rule the country.
I believe there is an answer
which would secure your future
and give you a position.
You can't be serious.
Just think about it.
I don't have
to think about it.
Marry a man who can barely hold
his knife like a gentleman?
Oh, you exaggerate.
BRUCE:
Women had absolutely
no position or power
until they were married,
so they had to find a man
who did.
Sir Anthony Strallan.
Sir Anthony!
Don't worry, Lady Grantham,
I haven't got the date wrong.
LAURA CARMICHAEL:
Women had a difficult time.
They didn't stand to gain
what sons would have done.
They had to find their fortune
in a good match,
in a good marriage.
The thing is,
I've got two tickets
for a concert in York
next Friday.
How nice.
Although I can't...
No, I was hoping that Lady Edith
might like to accompany me.
But I'd love to.
Excellent.
LAURA CARMICHAEL:
It was very important.
It was what women
were focused on
because it was the way
to leave home
and leave your parents behind
at last
and set up your own home.
BRUCE:
A young lady could not marry
until she had been presented
at court.
It was the start of a busy year
known as her "coming out."
JAMES:
I suppose "coming out"
was the most extreme example
of these rules and etiquette.
You had a train over your hair,
and the length of the train
was absolutely,
to a centimeter, controlled.
BRUCE:
From shoulder to floor,
trains measured no less
than three yards.
JAMES:
You just dressed up in white
with your feathers,
and it's all really specific,
how many feathers you have
in your hair.
BRUCE:
White dresses signified purity.
The number of feathers said
who was who.
Unmarried young ladies wore two,
married chaperones wore three.
MAN:
The Countess of Grantham,
presenting the
Lady Rose MacClare.
BRUCE:
A young lady's presentation
to the king and queen
was her entry into society.
It signaled she had
the monarch's blessing
as a suitable wife.
CREW:
Sound, speed.
And action.
That frock
really is yummy.
Thank you.
BRUCE:
Once she'd been presented
at court,
a young woman could attend
what was known as "the season,"
a round of parties where
she would meet eligible men.
How come I'm not
in my lieutenant's gear?
Because they're not...
There is no evening dress
for members of the lieutenancy
at this period.
Alastair is very useful
in providing context
and providing detail,
particularly around
the interaction between people.
I hope you got
everything done.
We wanted to clink our glasses
and say "cheers."
Well, women wouldn't have
clinked their glasses.
Cut and reset, please.
And they also wouldn't
have said "cheers."
So he sort of swooped in.
Can we talk
about that glass?
About saying "cheers"?
Yes, exactly right.
I'll just go,
"Your good health."
You want to say,
CREW:
Quiet, please.
And turnover.
Turning, turning, action!
CULLEN:
I love Alastair.
I mean, he literally
taught me everything--
how to tie my shoelaces,
how to gesture,
how to stand, ride a horse.
Um, he taught me
about the history of my family.
He's got this thing he calls
the posh bible,
which is this enormous book,
which I was...
I couldn't believe existed.
So he's in it.
Alastair can trace his line
all the way back
to Robert the Bruce,
you know, and further,
and they're all in this book.
BRUCE:
That thunderous book
is Burke's Peerage,
a list of every titled
aristocrat
in the United Kingdom.
A combination of background
check and bloodline,
an essential tool
for making a match.
CULLEN:
It's got nothing...
It's got absolutely nothing
to do with money.
This is what
the posh bible is about.
It's to show that it's got
nothing to do with money;
it's about your lineage
and your line
and about where you come from.
BRUCE:
Parents always used
Burke's Peerage
to check the family title
and status of potential suitors.
Their aim: a marriage
that enhanced the family.
CULLEN:
Lord Gillingham is able
to trace his lineage back
hundreds of years.
And so he has to marry
into certain families,
and there are certain names
and titles
that you have to match up to.
And it's like
a game of chess, politics.
I don't need
to explain to you
how the system
we're trapped in works.
Please don't rush
into anything.
I won't make a fool
of Mabel.
It wouldn't be fair.
CULLEN:
The system that
they're trapped in,
it's a set of rules, you know.
I mean, this is the thing
that shocked me most
about playing Lord Gillingham
was how repressed
and how stifled everything is.
Like how little emotion
you're allowed to show.
You're not allowed to laugh,
you're not allowed to love,
you're not allowed to...
You're certainly
not allowed to cry.
Um, and you have to marry
the people that your family
ask you to marry.
And so when, you know,
Gillingham says to Mary,
"We both understand the system
that we're trapped in,"
I think, for the first time
in his life,
he's telling somebody
that he loves them.
CREW:
Quiet, please!
Locking up outside.
How and who to marry
was fraught with complications
upstairs.
Downstairs, it was simple:
you just didn't.
VIOLET:
I was right about my maid.
She's leaving
to get married.
How could she be
so selfish?
Courtship is not permitted
amongst servants,
amongst the staff.
I don't know what...
Shh!
COYLE:
It was frowned upon,
so it's a very gentle,
drawn-out process.
Which I loved.
I love that process,
we both did,
so it was a very tender,
very delicate, incremental path
towards togetherness.
That's enough of that,
Mr. Bates.
We've work to do.
It did happen that servants
got married,
but actually in reality, the
woman would have left service.
BRUCE:
Marriage challenged your loyalty
to the family.
Service had to be your life.
And there was
a practical reason too:
men and women had separate
sleeping quarters in the house.
There was nowhere
for married couples to live.
So they're in quite a privileged
position really, Anna and Bates.
SOPHIE McSHERA:
Courting doesn't seem
to be really done downstairs
for Daisy especially,
because if she met him,
she'd have to go off with him,
so it would be rubbish for me,
I'd have to leave.
And there's also no time
to do much courting.
Bring the sauce boats for
Alfred, I'm doing the soufflés.
As soon as I've...
Will you just do it!
McSHERA:
You couldn't, you know,
court, go on a date,
and snog someone
or something like that.
I think that's why Daisy's
having such bad luck with men,
because she's basically got
the people around her
and that's it,
she never gets out.
Taxi!
BRUCE:
Aristocratic daughters
could go out.
But to meet a man alone
without a chaperone
was to risk their
good name forever.
(lively jazz playing)
JAMES:
I love that she's a party girl
at a time when you had
no independence.
Actually, she's being
incredibly brave
and she's actually making
a stand in that sense.
Jack Ross at your service.
I'm Rose MacClare,
how do you do?
Rose, I've been sent
to fetch you.
BRUCE:
Despite their privilege,
ladies' behavior
was tightly restricted.
CARMICHAEL:
When Edith goes to have dinner
at Gregson's flat,
she's not wearing gloves,
which was very shocking.
Did you miss me?
Of course.
Is it really only a week
until you leave?
Mmm.
You know,
she was practically naked.
Oh, my darling.
That is the evening
when she becomes pregnant,
so yes, she should have
worn gloves.
It really was the most
devastating thing,
to have a baby
out of wedlock.
Alastair sort of said to me,
he said, "All of this,"
pointing to the castle,
"Is based on the idea that you
will behave properly
"and you will be sort of someone
for people to look up to.
"That's what is expected.
"And if you don't
and, you know, you are shamed,
"then that really will destroy
your reputation in the county.
You know,
it'll go around London."
So in this series, there really
is a danger for Edith.
Isn't it time one of you
told me the truth?
If I told you the truth, Granny,
you'd never speak
to me again.
Then you have
told me the truth.
You'll share
the ownership.
It will be your house,
your estate as much as mine.
We will be
joint masters.
But...
BRUCE:
I love the glorious formality
of Edwardian life.
The rules they had to behave by
were a mixture
of straightforward practicality
and fear.
BONNEVILLE:
We shot a version
where our instincts were
entirely to hug,
as you would these days.
And of course
Alastair, you know,
threw his toys out of the pram
and said, "Don't be ridiculous.
You might just shake his hand--
just-- to express an emotion."
(laughing)
You are my darling daughter
and I love you,
hard as it is for an Englishman
to say the words.
BRUCE:
The British hadn't always
maintained a stiff upper lip.
Only a century earlier,
the passions
of the French Revolution
so terrified
the British aristocracy
that a cool reserve became the
definition of good character.
There was a very real fear
that without formality,
the authority
of the aristocracy would slip
and society would fall apart.
So the aristocracy
cultivated manners
that protected their position.
You don't understand.
I shall be Countess
of Grantham one day,
and in my book,
the Countess of Grantham
lives at Downton Abbey.
Being who they are
and the position
that they're in,
they are very outspoken people.
You know, Mary is someone
that if she has an opinion,
she'll say it,
and she says it with conviction
and she doesn't apologize
for it.
The tax people
have had a cancellation,
so they can see us
on Wednesday at noon.
But I think we should
go up tomorrow.
I wouldn't like to risk
being late.
It's confidence, actually.
It's having the confidence
to follow through
everything you say
and every thought you have
with conviction.
The world moves on
and we must move with it.
So you keep telling me.
They spoke very loudly
because, you know, they had
a right to be heard
and they weren't afraid
of their opinion,
and everyone listened
when they spoke
because they're the aristocracy,
and that's that!
And also, these vast,
big rooms they spoke in.
When's Cousin Robert
coming back?
I don't know,
I wish I did.
We've had no word
from him in days.
CULLEN:
The oddest thing is that
you have to be incredibly rude
to be an Edwardian.
And posh, you have to be
very rude to be posh.
We don't say thank you
for things.
When you're given a cup of tea,
you wouldn't acknowledge the
person who's giving it to you.
So you pretend that
they're not there.
All my instincts inside scream
that this is so rude,
this is so rude
to be ignoring the person
who's helping you out,
doing something.
But it's just the way it was.
BRUCE:
The way it was was simply
practical to the Edwardians.
I don't want you
to stand in line.
I want you to rush
to that door.
To be served 30 times a day
and to say thank you every time
would have been maddening.
So the rule was
silent appreciation.
CARMICHAEL:
The servants that
pride themselves
on being the best servants
are practically, you know,
invisible in those moments.
My husband is dead.
Can't you understand
what that means?
After all he suffered
in the war,
he's killed
in a stupid car crash.
SPELEERS:
We see everything,
we hear everything,
but we've got to behave
like we don't,
so almost like a blank face.
But there's a lot of information
that can be taken in obviously
because it's impossible
not to take it in.
Well, they do, they just talk
in front of the servants
because they assume that
it will go over their heads.
Well, of course it doesn't.
TOM:
He's asked me
to go in with him.
A brother
who's coming to stay?
Yes-- Kieran.
Also, that's the entertainment
for the people downstairs.
You know, for everyone
downstairs, for the staff,
that's their soap opera.
BRUCE:
However dramatic
the entertainment,
the servants were trusted
to be utterly discreet.
Is there some crisis
of which I am unaware?
No, Mr. Carson.
The first rule of being a
servant upstairs is discretion.
We do not discuss the business
of this house with strangers.
They may gossip
between themselves downstairs,
but it certainly
wouldn't be something
they'd want
to leave the house
because they wouldn't want
to be working for the house
that was center of the gossip.
You know, they want to be seen
as working for one of the best
houses in the country,
you know, because that's
their status symbol.
BRUCE:
The Edwardians were terrified
of scandal
because the newspapers
had just discovered
how marketable
gossip could be.
For the first time,
tittle-tattle wasn't just local;
the whole country
could suddenly know your shame.
CORA:
What happened?
I don't know!
Yes, somebody died in Lady
Mary's bed, goodness gracious.
He was alive
and suddenly he cried out
and then he was dead.
(whispering):
But why was he here at all?
FROGGATT:
And you know,
if anyone found out
about this incident,
Lady Mary would really be
a pariah, you know,
from society.
It would be a terrible thing.
I'll be ruined, Mama.
Ruined and notorious.
A laughing stock,
a social pariah.
Is that what you want
for your eldest daughter?
Is it what you want
for the family?
So for the good of the house
and for the good
of Lady Mary's reputation,
you know, it's Anna's job
to go above and beyond
the call of duty
and help move a dead body
from time to time.
(groans)
Mama!
Sorry!
McGOVERN:
Cora has no other choice
in the Pamuk situation.
I mean, she's very well aware
that it does mean
absolute social death for Mary
on all levels
at a very young age.
And, um, she's very much aware
of what a terrible blow
that would be for her.
Anna.
I will not insult you
by asking that you also conceal
Lady Mary's shame.
Let us go.
If the first rule of being
a good servant is discretion,
then the second is never
to burden your master
with your own problems.
I'm John Bates, the new valet.
The new valet?
That's right.
COYLE:
He arrives at the house
and he's not welcome at all,
and he's not
up to the task.
So Lord Grantham says
basically,
"This isn't working,
I'm gonna have to let you go."
The thing is, Bates,
I said I'd give you a trial
and I have.
COYLE:
Losing the job would mean,
for a man of his age
and this disability,
it would be straight
to the workhouse.
It would be over.
You do see that Carson
can't be expected
to compromise the efficiency
of his staff.
I do, m'lord,
of course I do.
Bates wants to implore,
as anybody would.
He'd want to implore this man,
"Please, I'll do anything.
"What can I do?
"I'll try this.
Well, how can we work this out?"
But he can't and he wouldn't.
So he says...
Might I make
a suggestion that
when an extra footman
is required,
the costs could come out
of my wages.
Absolutely not,
I couldn't possibly allow that.
Because I am very eager
to stay, m'lord.
Very eager indeed.
It's very delicately put,
but it's loaded with a pleading
which the man doesn't express,
nor would he.
And once Lord Grantham says...
I mean to help
until you find something.
There's a finality to that
that both men know.
Very good, m'lord.
I'll go at once.
There's no need to rush out
into the night.
Take the London train tomorrow.
It leaves at 9:00.
COYLE:
And ostensibly,
it's over for Bates.
All in that tiny scene,
so much that is unsaid is said.
It's a bloody business,
Bates,
but I can't see
any way around it.
I quite understand, m'lord.
COYLE:
It would be unseemly, it would
be crude to be emotional,
and to impose that on somebody
would put them
in an awkward position.
There are many records
of servants
giving emotional support
to their masters and mistresses.
But if the servants
face troubles,
they'd probably face them alone.
What I want is
to go back upstairs.
You're not telling me
that sad old cripple
keeps you happy.
If you must know, yes,
he keeps me very happy.
Now let me by, please.
Perhaps you've forgotten
what you're missing.
FROGGATT:
When I found out
about Anna's rape storyline,
I was, you know,
trying to get my head around
what that meant for a woman
of her class in her time.
Because, you know,
when I read the scripts,
I, like a lot of other people,
really wanted Anna
to tell someone,
for this man to be brought
to justice, you know?
But Alastair said to me,
"You know, you have to remember
for a working-class woman,
all she had was her reputation."
We must tell somebody.
No, no, no, no.
But you have
to tell Mr. Bates.
Him least of all!
If he knew, he'd murder
the man who's done it
and then he'd be hanged.
FROGGATT:
In reality,
if anybody would have found out
what happened to her,
then she would have, you know,
brought disrepute on the house,
she would have brought disrepute
on herself,
she probably would have
lost her job.
Nobody else must ever know.
You promise me?
FROGGATT:
To us, that sounds totally
barbaric, thank goodness.
You know, it's remembering we're
only 100 years on from that.
And that was a real
eye-opener for me.
It's a strange relationship
between servants and masters--
very close,
but bound by rules.
(bell rings)
There are certain rules
within the house.
There is the etiquette,
there is the decorum,
there is the upkeep,
there are the rules.
You would never ask
a personal question.
Good day, m'lord?
Good until tonight.
I took a walloping
from Mr. Sampson.
You would never prompt
a conversation.
I was a fool
to play with someone
who so obviously knew
what he was doing.
COYLE:
You certainly wouldn't say
anything judgmental
about his lordship's actions
or thoughts,
no matter what I was thinking.
Perhaps keep it
to yourself, Bates.
Of course, m'lord.
Good man.
It's almost like confession.
It's almost like a Catholic
thing where, you know,
it's a sanctuary.
The trouble is
being dressed and undressed
is an intimate business.
We've forgiven Thomas
his early sins, I know,
but I cannot imagine I would
ever quite feel the trust.
Say no more, m'lord.
I'm sure Mr. Bates
will be home soon,
which will settle
the matter.
COYLE:
It's an extraordinary thing.
On the one hand,
there's a decorum there.
There are boundaries
in terms of what can be said
and what can't be said,
while at the same time,
you're putting
a man's trousers on.
BONNEVILLE:
Bates knows everything
about my personal life,
as indeed Anna knows
everything about Mary.
So it's a very one-sided
relationship.
How was dinner?
Uphill.
I'm so bored of Mr. Blake's
cold shoulder.
He hasn't warmed up, then?
Lady Mary and Anna do have
a very close relationship,
and I would say
they were friends as well.
But they are still, you know,
a servant and master.
According to Mr. Napier,
he finds me aloof.
I'm not aloof, am I?
Do you want me
to answer truthfully
or like a lady's maid?
Let's move on.
DOCKERY:
Anna is always aware
of her position,
whereas Mary
sometimes forgets.
She forgets herself
and she forgets Anna's position,
so she'll tell her much more
than she needs to.
BRUCE:
The intimacy of these
relationships was inevitable.
They spent so much time together
endlessly dressing
and undressing.
Clothes mattered
to the Edwardians
because every detail
meant something.
The aristocracy
wore impractical,
high-maintenance clothing
that proclaimed privilege.
It sort of said,
"I don't have to do any work
and I have help
putting this on."
A great deal of effort
went into making sure
that ladies and gentlemen
appeared effortless.
And why?
Because it said,
"We're in charge."
Edith, what are you
thinking?
You know, I don't dislike him
as much as you do.
Perhaps you don't
dislike him at all.
Perhaps I don't.
BRUCE:
Ladies' dress was
extravagantly elaborate
and guided by myriad rules.
CARMICHAEL:
I'm not allowed
to wear a tiara
because...
You only wear a tiara
if you're married.
(laughing): Not sure
about the rules on pearls.
Only that I don't get
to wear any.
You look beautiful.
Thank you,
Sybil darling.
JAMES:
Then there's the whole thing
of gloves--
when you have your gloves on,
when you have them off.
Even in the drawing room.
How long are they
going to stay?
You have to leave your gloves on
like pre- and post-dinner.
We sort of have them
all the time, you know?
We have traveling gloves
and dinner gloves
and riding gloves.
Is there anything more thrilling
than a new frock?
BRUCE:
Such dress codes began centuries
earlier in the sumptuary laws.
These originally forbade anyone
but the nobility
from wearing things
like fur or silk.
On a usual day, you know,
they'll dress for breakfast
and then they'll maybe change
if they go for a walk
in the morning
or go riding,
then they'll change for lunch.
Then they may change
for the afternoon
to sit and read
or go and visit someone,
and then they'll change again
for dinner.
Basically, these ladies
just spend most
of their time changing.
McGOVERN:
You couldn't really do much
in any of those clothes
because we were corseted,
and you're cinched in
and your ribs
are pulled together,
you're not getting the same
amount of oxygen to your brain
that you would normally.
So it creates
a very passive personality.
Golly,
my corset's tight.
Anna, when you've
done that,
would you be an angel
and loosen it a bit?
The start
of the slippery slope.
CREW:
Sound, speed.
McGOVERN:
It isn't so applicable now
because we're now in 1924
and the clothes were giving us
much more license
to freely move, think, talk,
eat, do everything.
And I don't think
it's a coincidence
that women were
suddenly demanding
to have their opinions heard
and demanding to find a use
for themselves as people
because they could
actually breathe!
BRUCE:
Clothes for gentlemen
remained resolutely stiff,
a statement of control
in a shifting world.
Right, I'm off
to collect Matthew.
You look very smart.
I hope so, because I'm
extremely uncomfortable.
I've got a multitude of suits,
and the dinner suit
is maybe the worst thing
I've ever worn in my life.
You have to literally
screw yourself
into this starch-ironed,
cardboard kind of shirt.
They're so horrible
because what it means
is that you can't bend
or anything.
So you just have to stand there
with your hands by your side,
pretend to be a penguin,
basically.
The clothes you wear
alter the way you move
and the way you feel.
I mean,
I was noticing yesterday,
even between scenes,
there's no slouching
because you just simply can't.
You know, dressing for dinner
or dressing several times a day,
certainly for the girls,
you couldn't do this
on your own.
You'd need help.
It's like getting
into a suit of armor.
Well, I'm glad
that's settled.
CULLEN:
Don't talk to me about hats.
So many hats
for so many different occasions.
Why does somebody need
so many hats?
CREW:
And action!
BRUCE:
Hats were terribly important.
In an instant,
your hat said who you were.
Well, all around you,
you can see lots
of different kinds of hats.
Very difficult to set a rule,
but on the whole,
if you were somewhere
at the top of society--
you were an aristocrat
with a huge house--
you were allowed to wear
a top hat for smart occasions.
And you'd wear
whatever was comfortable
because you had the money
and the capability
to go through all the different
fashionable hats
that were available,
right down to the cloth cap,
which if you were a working
class man is where you'd stay.
And so where you see
cloth caps here,
they're probably
working-class people
and they can't afford
a bowler hat, very expensive.
Lord Grantham will today
be wearing a trilby
because it's just
quite debonair, quite smart,
and he's going out
into his own village.
I mean,
he owns everything here,
so he feels he doesn't need
to show off to anybody.
But Carson with him,
Carson's always on duty
and he'll be wearing
his bowler hat
because that's his smartest
and he's with his boss.
(laughing)
CREW:
Here we go, rehearsal.
BRUCE:
People wore hats in this time,
and it was just part of their
"going out of doors" routine.
But you used it as a means
of being polite,
and normally just
doffed your hat at somebody
out of courtesy,
or a woman.
But what also happened is that
if you were actually
having a conversation
with someone of your own degree,
you'd take your hat off
and you'd talk to them.
CREW:
Check, please.
Do we take
the hat off?
What I was keen for you to do
is to take your hat off,
so you're being
very generous doing that,
whereas I think Carson's
just gonna doff
and then realize
you've done that,
so he'll take his off too.
But no hand shaking.
No.
Mark.
Good day, m'lord,
Mr. Carson.
Mrs. Elcot,
what are you up to?
Oh, I'm just waiting
for our Robbie.
He likes to say hello
to his father sometimes
when he comes
out of school.
BRUCE:
I was worried that
they'd try and shake hands
with gloves on.
Disaster.
People just didn't
shake hands then
because they were terrified
of picking up diseases.
Hello, I'm Alastair Bruce,
the historical advisor.
Hello, I'm Naomi,
nice to meet you.
Naomi, may I ask you...
Not to do that?
Well, could you
bring it up a bit?
Yes, just a little
bit more.
That's perfect.
743, take one.
I'm just waiting
for our Robbie.
He comes with me
if I go to the shop
or the post office.
Takes chance
to visit the grave then.
Cut!
BRUCE:
I think what all of this
is about
is trying to remember status.
Robert understands,
as an aristocrat,
that he's in charge
of everything.
But Carson understands status
and feels it
more than anybody else
because below stairs,
it really counts where you are
in the pecking order.
Lord Grantham is in charge
by virtue of his position.
The aristocracy was expected
to live off its land.
There was no question
of actually having to find work.
I've got a job in Ripon.
I said I'll start tomorrow.
A job?
Making money
and working nine to five
fills the minds of most of us,
while yearning for the weekend.
But for the early
20th century aristocrat,
this couldn't have been further
from his thinking.
And what is a weekend?
BRUCE:
Getting a job and making money
simply wasn't necessary.
You inherited your house
and the land,
or you married one.
And then the land made you money
and life was good.
You do not love
the place yet?
Well, obviously, it's...
No, you don't love it.
You see a million bricks
that may crumble,
a thousand gutters
and pipes
that may block and leak,
and stone that will crack
in the frost.
But you don't?
I see my life's work.
BRUCE:
But their undisputed status
as lords of the manor
was threatened by men
with new money--
men like Sir Richard Carlisle--
ambitious men
with pretentions to grandeur.
Hello.
We're so pleased to have
you here, Sir Richard.
Lady Grantham.
Welcome.
Thank you.
I hope the train
wasn't too tiring.
Not a bit, no,
I got a lot done.
New money was loud, strident
and successful.
The aristocracy
had to counter this
by labeling any mention
of money as common.
The English upper classes
never talk about money?
We don't like to.
But you don't mind
thinking about it.
That's like the rich who say
that money doesn't matter.
It matters enough
when you haven't got it.
I know you don't care
about our silly rules.
You're always very clear
on that score.
You make me sound rude.
But I'm not ashamed of being
what they call a self-made man.
BONNEVILLE:
I think there's a very
interesting difference
between someone like Carlisle
in series two and Robert.
Carlisle comes
from a meritocracy
based on, you know,
the work you've done
and the finance you've earned.
His social status comes
from the business he's set up.
Whereas, you know, Robert
has been born into this society,
into this structure.
His sole purpose in life
is to maintain the estate
and to hand it on
in as good a nick
as he possibly can
to the next generation.
BRUCE:
But the certainty
of landed wealth,
which the aristocracy
had enjoyed for centuries,
was starting to fail.
Grain supplies
from North America
drove down the value of crops,
and tax reforms threatened
inherited wealth.
ROBERT:
My fortune is the work
of others.
I am a custodian, my dear,
not an owner.
I must strive to be worthy
of the task I've been set.
BONNEVILLE:
Robert's not a businessman.
He has a shrewd idea
about how to treat people,
he has a great respect
for other people,
but in terms of running
a small economy,
no, he's not your man.
So that's been, you know,
a lot of fun
playing with some
of the problems
that the modern day presents
to someone like Robert.
Why not tackle it
gradually?
Perhaps buy some time
by investing your capital.
I hear of schemes every day
that'll double whatever's put
into them or triple it or more.
Many schemes offer high rewards,
very few deliver them.
Well, there's a chap in America,
what's his name--
Charles Ponzi--
who offers a huge return
after 90 days.
Robert of course is the guy
who, you know, thinks
Ponzi's a great guy,
or, you know, there's,
"Everybody's piling
into the Canadian Railways,
let's do that."
Harry Stoke has gone in
with a bundle.
Then Harry Stoke,
whoever he is, is a fool.
But it I could find out...
Robert, the last time you took
an interest in investment,
you ruined the family!
Robert, who appears at times
to be a dinosaur,
and sometimes is, but he's
actually trying to conserve
the best of the old and the new,
and to make sure that the estate
continues to function
to the best of its ability.
BRUCE:
The best of the old
meant a job and a home for life
to servants like Molesley.
Only misbehavior or misfortune
would cost you your position.
DOYLE:
Molesley finds himself surplus
to needs.
And you realize very quickly,
as people nowadays realize,
actually, that you're only
a couple of paychecks away
from, you know, desperation.
Hello, Mr. Molesley.
How are things?
Well, as you can see,
not very good.
I don't agree.
It's skilled work.
No, it isn't,
not what I'm doing.
I'm sure if you just wait,
something better will turn up.
I have waited
and nothing's turned up.
I haven't earned a penny
since Mr. Crawley died.
Now I owe money
all over the village.
Yes, but surely
with your skill...
Don't you understand
I'm at my wits' end?
FROGGATT:
Money wasn't a subject
that was spoken about
in polite conversation,
nor were intense emotions
either.
So it's quite shocking for Anna.
I apologize,
I should not have said that.
It was vulgar
and self-important.
Please forgive me.
BONNEVILLE:
There is no social welfare
system,
there is no healthcare system,
and the people
who work on your estate
live or die by your hand,
really,
by the way you treat them.
BRUCE:
On set, our work
is just as elaborate
as the servants' work was
for a great Edwardian family.
Where's the other rake?
I think you've probably got
quite a lot in there.
It's just,
I love gravel.
To me, gravel makes
all the difference.
Do you notice how
with the raking,
it looks completely different,
and with all these old houses,
the gravel would have been raked
first thing in the morning
every single day,
and if necessary,
later on too.
BONNEVILLE:
It goes back to this thing,
this analogy I've used
in the past
of the estate really being
a whole load of cogs
that service the one machine.
And if you take out a cog
because you think
it's either, you know,
not gonna work properly
or simply because you can't be
bothered to oil it or something,
then the whole machine
starts to break down.
BRUCE:
Can you make
a tighter line?
There.
There, hands by your side.
Knowing your place
was the first rule and the last.
It's the point
from which all manners sprang.
But it wasn't just
the lower orders
who had to know
where they belonged;
the aristocrats
had to get it right too.
I've been meaning to speak
to you about Molesley.
Oh?
Would you find me
very ungrateful
if I dispensed
with his services?
Why? Has he displeased you
in some way?
Not at all.
It's simply that
he's superfluous
to our style of living.
Is that quite fair,
to deprive a man
of his livelihood
when he's done
nothing wrong?
Well, I wouldn't
quite put it...
Your mother derives satisfaction
from her work at the hospital,
I think,
some sense of self-worth.
Well, certainly.
Would you really deny the same
to poor old Molesley?
And when you
are master here,
is the butler to be dismissed,
or the footman?
How many maids or kitchen staff
will be allowed to stay,
or must every one be driven out?
We all have different parts
to play, Matthew,
and we must all be allowed
to play them.
BRUCE:
The key to the aristocrat's
view of the world
was not privilege;
it was duty.
The point of an aristocrat
was to be of use
to the land he owned
and its people.
Robert owns everything
he can see-- all this.
It's a kingdom of 6,000 acres,
a miniature economy
that depends on his lordship's
successful reign.
MATTHEW:
I don't know
about the rest of you,
but I sometimes think it's time
we lived in a simpler way.
VIOLET:
Oh, don't say that.
It's our job
to provide employment.
An aristocrat
with no servants
is as much use to the county
as a glass hammer.
(laughs)
It's not just a rich man
in his big castle
served by the lower orders.
Grantham serves them
by keeping all this going
and by giving each
a respectable place
in the mighty machine
that was Great Britain.
It was the perfect balance
between privilege
and responsibility.
CREW:
Action!
Hold it there,
thank you.
The thing that strikes me,
as I struggle to make sure
everyone stands up straight
and avoids hugging,
is that what we regard
as strange and formal
to them was as natural
as the air they breathed.
The real secret behind
the manners of Downton Abbey
and the thing we all work
so hard to get right
is that for them,
this was effortless.